Chapter 101. The decanter.
Heir. The English ship fades from sight.
Be it sat down here that she hailed from London and was named after the late
Samuel Enderby, merchant of that city, the original of the famous Whailing
House of Enderbean Sons. A house which, in my poor whaleman's opinion, comes not
far behind the United Royal Houses of the Tutors and Bourbons, in point of
real historical interest. How long, prior to the year of our Lord, 1775,
this great whailing house was in existence, my numerous fish documents do
not make plain. But in that year, 1775, it fitted out the first English ships
that ever regularly hunted the sperm whale. Though for some score of years
previous, ever since 1726, our valiant coffins and maces of
Nantucket in the vineyard had in large fleets pursued that Leviathan, but only
in the North and South Atlantic, not elsewhere. Be it distinctly recorded
here that the Nantucketers were the first among mankind to harpoon with
civilized steel the great sperm whale and that for a half century they were
the only people of the whole globe who so harpooned him.
In 1778, a fine ship, the Amelia, fitted out for the express purpose, and at the
sole charge of the vigorous Enderbees, boldly rounded Cape Horn, and was the
first among the nations to lower a whaleboat of any sort in the great South
Sea. The voyage was a skillful and lucky one, and returning to her birth with her
hold full of the precious sperm, the Amelia's example was soon followed by
other ships, English and American, and thus the vast sperm whale grounds of the
Pacific were thrown open. But not content with this good deed, the
inddehatigable house again burred itself. Samuel and all his sons, how
many their mother only knows, and under their immediate opaces, and partly, I
think, at their expense, the British government was induced to send the sloop
of war rattler on a whailing voyage of discovery into the South Seas. Commanded
by a naval post captain, the rattler made a rattling voyage of it, and did
some service. How much does not appear?
But this is not all. In 1819, the same house fitted out a discovery whale ship
of their own to go on a tasting cruise to the remote waters of Japan. That
ship, well called the Siren, made a noble experimental cruise, and it was
thus that the great Japanese whailing ground first became generally known. The
Siren in this famous voyage was commanded by a captain coffin, a Nantucketer.
All honor to the Enderbees, therefore, whose house, I think, exists to the
present day, though doubtless the original Samuel must long ago have
slipped his cable for the great South Sea of the other world.
The ship named after him was worthy of the honor, being a very fast sailor and
a noble craft in every way. I boarded her once at midnight somewhere off the
Patagonian coast, and drank good flip down in the folks. It was a fine gam we
had, and they were all trumps, every soul on board. A short life to them and
a jolly death. And that fine gam I had long, very long after old Ahab touched
her planks with his ivory heel, it reminds me of the noble, solid saxs and
hospitality of that ship. And may my parson forget me, and the devil remember
me if ever I lose sight of it. Flip? Did
I say we had flip? Yes, and we flipped it at the rate of 10 gallons the hour,
and when the squall came, poured it squally off there by Patagonia, in all
hands visitors and all were called to reef top sails, we were so topheavy that
we had to swing each other aloft in bolands, and we ignorantly furled the
skirts of our jackets into the sails, so that we hung there reefed fast in the
howling gale, a warning example to all drunken tars. However, the mass did not
go overboard, and by and by we scrambled down, so sober that we had to pass the
flip again, though the savage salt spray bursting down the folks scuttle rather
too much diluted and pickled it to my taste.
The beef was fine, tough, but with body in it. They said it was bull beef,
others that it was dramadary beef, but I do not know for certain how that was.
They had dumplings, too. Small but substantial, symmetrically globular and
indestructible dumplings. I fancied you could feel them and roll them about in
you after they were swallowed. If you stooped over too far forward, you risked
their pitching out of you like billiard balls. The bread, but that couldn't be
helped. Besides, it was an anti-scorputic.
In short, the bread contained the only fresh fair they had, but the folks was
not very light, and it was very easy to step over into a dark corner when you
ate it. But all in all, taking her from truck to helm, considering the
dimensions of the cook's boilers, including his own live parchment
boilers, for an aft, I say, the Samuel Enderbe was a jolly ship of good fair
and plenty, fine flip and strong, crackfellows all, and capital from boot heels to hatband.
But why was it think you that the Samuel Enderbe and some other English whalers I
know of, not all though, were such famous, hospitable ships that passed
round the beef and the bread and the can and the joke, and were not soon weary of
eating and drinking and laughing. I will tell you the abounding good cheer of
these English whalers is a matter for historical research. Nor have I been at
all sparing of historical whale research when it is seemed needed.
The English were preceded in the whale fishery by the Hollanders, Zealanders,
and Danes, from whom they derived many terms still extant in the fishery, and
what is yet more, their fat old fashions, touching plenty to eat and
drink. For as a general thing, the English merchant ship scrimps her crew,
but not so the English whaler. Hence, in the English, this thing of whailing good
cheer is not normal and natural, but incidental in particular, and therefore
must have some special origin, which is here pointed out, and will be still further elucidated.
During my researches in the Leviathanic histories, I stumbled upon an ancient
Dutch volume, which by the musty whailing smell of it, I knew must be
about whalers. The title was Dan Coupeman, wherefore I concluded that
this must be the invaluable memoirs of some Amsterdam cooper in the fishery, as
every whale ship must carry its Cooper.
I was reinforced in this opinion by seeing that it was the production of one
Fitz Swackhammer. But my friend Dr.
Snodthead, a very learned man, professor of low Dutch and high German in the
college of Santa Claus and St. Pots, to whom I handed the work for translation,
giving him a box of sperm candles for his trouble. This same Dr. Snodthead, so
soon as he spied the book, assured me that Dan Coupeman did not mean the
Cooper, but the merchant. In short, this ancient and learned low Dutch book
treated of the commerce of Holland, and among other subjects, contained a very
interesting account of its whale fishery. And in this chapter it was
headed smear or fat that I found a long detailed list of the outfits for the
larders and sellers of 180 sale of Dutch whalemen from which list translated by
Dr. Snodthead. I transcribed the following.
400,000 lb of beef, 60,000 lb freezeland pork,
150,000 lb of stockfish, 550,000 lb of biscuit, 72,000 lb of soft bread, 2,800
firins of butter, 20,000 lb texl and liden cheese, 144,000 lb cheese, probably an inferior
article, 550 anchors of Geneva, 10,800 barrels of beer.
Most statistical tables are parchingly dry in the reading, not so in the
present case, however, where the reader is flooded with whole pipes, barrels,
quartz, and gills of good jin and good cheer.
At the time, I devoted three days to the studious digesting of all this beer,
beef, and bread, during which many profound thoughts were incidentally
suggested to me, capable of a transcendental and platonic application.
And furthermore, I compiled supplementary tables of my own, touching
the probable quantity of stockfish, etc., consumed by every low Dutch
harpooner in that ancient Greenland and Spitsburg and whale fishery. In the
first place, the amount of butter and texel and liden cheese consumed seems
amazing. I impute it, though, to their naturally anxious natures, being
rendered still more anxious by the nature of their vocation, and especially
by their pursuing their game in those frigid polar seas on the very coasts of
that Eskimo country where the convivial natives pledge each other in bumpers of train oil.
The quantity of beer too is very large, 10,800 barrels. Now, as those polar
fisheries could only be prosecuted in the short summer of that climate, so
that the whole crews of one of these Dutch whalemen, including the short
voyage to and from the Spitsburg and sea, did not much exceed 3 months, say,
and reckoning 30 men to each of their fleet of 180 sail, we have 5,400 low
Dutch seaman in all. Therefore, I say we have precisely two barrels of beer per
man for a 12 weeks allowance, exclusive of his fair proportion of that 550
anchors of jin. Now, whether these jin and beer harpooners, so fuddled as one
might fancy them to have been, were the right sort of men to stand up in a
boat's head and take good aim at flying whales, this would seem somewhat
improbable. Yet, they did aim at them and hit them, too. But this was very far
north, be it remembered, where beer agrees well with the constitution. Upon
the equator, in our southern fishery, beer would be apt to make the harpooner
sleepy at the mast head and boozy in his boat, and grievous loss might ensue to
Nantucket and New Bedford.
But no more. Enough has been said to show that the old Dutch whalers of two
or three centuries ago were high livers, and that the English whalers have not
neglected so excellent an example. For say they, when cruising in an empty
ship, if you can get nothing better out of the world, get a good dinner out of
it at least. And this empties the decanter.